Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's daf דף daf is Chaf
Aleph כ"א, Chaf Aleph, 21. And we pick up on Chaf Amud
Bet כ' עמוד ב', Chaf Amud Bet, two lines down in the
wide lines. We're dealing still with an eved Ivri עבד עברי eved
Ivri issue,
and here we go. And the one of the most recent things
was about the idea about how do you know that if the
price changes, you redeem him and you're redeeming him based on the
amount of service left, it can go to, it would be based
on the lesser of the purchase price and of the current market
price.
And along there the Gemara גמרא Gemara actually had some interesting aggadata
אגדתא aggadata or value statements, a number one or partly also halachic
הלכתי, halachic, that a person who buys an eved Ivri עבד עברי
eved Ivri has to treat him equal or better, as so supposedly
better than himself, if not, if not equal, but minimally equal to
himself. And so therefore it's like a disincentive to buy an eved
Ivri עבד עברי. eved Ivri. And then clearly it read the parsha
פרשה parsha in Behar בהר Behar that selling oneself as an eved
Ivri עבד עברי eved Ivri is only in the most desperate of
circumstances as a result of sin and so on. And nevertheless, even
when a person gets himself deep into it and has sold himself
to a non-Jew, sold himself to ovdei avodah zarah עובדי עבודה זרה,
ovdei avodah zarah, actually to a house of idolatry, nevertheless, it's our
responsibility to redeem the person. Now, it's worth pointing out right here
that in the Torah תורה, Torah, the Torah תורה Torah is only
explicit that the relatives have an obligation to redeem in two cases:
when a person sells a sdeh achuza שדה אחוזה, sdeh achuza, a
field of an ancestral field, and when a person sells himself into
as a slave to a non-Jew. It does not deal with a
case of selling a house if there's an obligation to redeem there,
and it does not deal with the case of selling oneself to
a Jew. Okay, so those are the only cases in the Torah
תורה: Torah: the selling of the ancestral field and selling oneself to
a non-Jew.
Now, there's other sense also, is that non-sell?
Yeah, but that scenario is not in the Torah תורה, Torah, but
I'm talking specifically, that's anyway a different case. You're right. I mean,
we use the word like to redeem. But here it's like a
buyback is really more what this is. Okay, two lines down in
the wide lines. Baie minei Rav Huna bar Chinena me-Rav Sheshet בעי
מיניה רב הונא בר חיננא מרב ששת. Baie minei Rav Huna bar
Chinena me-Rav Sheshet. Eved Ivri hanimkar le-ovdei kochavim עבד עברי הנמכר לעובד
כוכבים, Eved Ivri hanimkar le-ovdei kochavim, nigal lachatzo'in o eino nigal lachatzo'in
נגאל לחצאין או אינו נגאל לחצאין? nigal lachatzo'in o eino nigal lachatzo'in?
Sold to a non-Jew, so he has, there's this obligation to redeem
him. Now, can he be redeemed halfway or not? Now, what does
it mean halfway? So we'll see in a minute how that would
play out. But let's first hear the question. Ge'ulato ge'ulato mi-sdeh achuza
gamar גאולתו גאולתו משדה אחוזה גמר. Ge'ulato ge'ulato mi-sdeh achuza gamar. Do
we make a gezerah shava גזירה שוה gezerah shava from the redemption
of an ancestral field? Ma sdeh achuza eino nigal lachatzo'in מה שדה
אחוזה אינו נגאל לחצאין, Ma sdeh achuza eino nigal lachatzo'in, by an
ancestral field you cannot redeem halfway. How do we know? Because by
the ancestral field it says, 'u-matza k'dei ge'ulato ומצא כדי גאולתו,' u-matza
k'dei ge'ulato, that the person is able to put together the sufficient
funds for redeeming it. U-matza k'dei ge'ulato ומצא כדי גאולתו. U-matza k'dei
ge'ulato. So the implication is only when you have the full amount.
Anything less than the full amount would not work. That's the case
of sdeh achuza שדה אחוזה. sdeh achuza. Ma sdeh achuza eino nigal
lachatzo'in af hai nami eino nigal lachatzo'in מה שדה אחוזה אינו נגאל
לחצאין אף האי נמי אינו נגאל לחצאין, Ma sdeh achuza eino nigal
lachatzo'in af hai nami eino nigal lachatzo'in, here too, it would not
be halfway. O dilma lekula amrinan lechumra lo amrinan או דילמא לקולא
אמרינן לחומרא לא אמרינן, O dilma lekula amrinan lechumra lo amrinan, we
would link it to a sdeh achuza שדה אחוזה sdeh achuza to
be lenient on the redemption aspects but not to be strict. Now
we're going to see in a minute what this lenient and strict
would mean. Amar lei lav amarta ha אמר ליה לאו אמרת הא,
Amar lei lav amarta ha, well, you know, let me just pause
for a moment and say something so we're not just totally in
abeyance. So what does it mean redeemed halfway? So Rashi רש"י Rashi
says something which is pretty radical. If you look at what's not
the point that the Gemara גמרא Gemara says explicitly. If you look
at Rashi רש"י, Rashi, Rashi רש"י Rashi says at the end, 'lachatzo'in
לחצאין,' lachatzo'in, the last of the narrower of the top wide lines,
Rashi רש"י Rashi says at the end, 'higi'a yado le-dmei chatzi ge'ono
הגיע ידו לדמי חצי גאונו,' higi'a yado le-dmei chatzi ge'ono, you're able
to buy back half of your value. 'Niyam ve-yama'it chatzi shaniv me-alav
ניים וימעיט חצי שניו מעליו,' Niyam ve-yama'it chatzi shaniv me-alav, you can
give it and, at least the way Rashi רש"י Rashi makes it
sound like, if I now have enough money, I have four years
left and I have now enough money for two years, I can
buy back two years and I get off at the end of
two years, not at the end of four years. Okay, that's huge,
right? So you can just cut down your service, you know, and
paying off, but then you cut down the amount of service. That
makes sense, two years
later for the same price.
I understand, that's not what the Gemara גמרא Gemara says. I mean
the Gemara גמרא Gemara doesn't say against that but that's not the
case the Gemara גמרא Gemara says. The case the Gemara גמרא Gemara
is about to say is the following, I'll just tell it to
you. Let's say that there is four years left and a current
market value those four years is worth 400 dollars. Okay, and I
get 200 dollars, and I get 200 dollars. I give the 200
dollars. Now I'm half redeemed, okay? And now tomorrow the market drops
down, and now my, oh no, let's say it's double. The market
shoots up tomorrow and now my four years are worth 800 dollars.
How much do I now have to pay to finish paying to
finish redeeming myself? If I was half redeemed, then I only would
have to pay half that, 400, right? Because I've already paid off
half. So although the remaining of the service is 800, half of
that has been paid off. It's like paying off your mortgage, right?
Half of that has been paid off. So you only have to
pay the remainder, the half of the 800, which is 400. If
however that doesn't count as anything, if I want now I'd have
to pay the full eight hundred or six hundred in addition to
my two hundred. Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara says. רש"י,
Rashi, we'll see that in a minute, but רש"י Rashi sounds like
you could actually shrink the amount of service left. Anyway, that's the
question. Do we say this by an עבד עברי? eved Ivri? We
do not, we know we do not say it by a שדה
אחוזה. sdeh achuza. Okay, so אמר ליה, amar leh,
the question of service or just of money, and
how do you, right, what is the remaining balance? What's the total
amount?
In any case,
the גמרא Gemara is not distinguishing at this stage. Okay, אמר ליה,
amar leh, he said back to him,
but לא אמרת התם? lo amarta hatam? Wait a minute, we say
over there, נמכר כולו ולא חציו. nimkar kulo v'lo chetzya. Remember when
we talked about the person sold בגנבתו, b'gnevato, that they do not
sell him, right, whatever, but the relevant point here is, it says
ונמכר, v'nimkar, you know, it says בגנבתו, b'gnevato, that only if his
value was more than the גנבה, gneva, you wouldn't sell him, because
you sell all of him, not part of him. הכא נמי נגאל
כולו ולא חציו. hacha nami nigaal kulo v'lo chetzya. Here too, even
without a גזרה שוה, gzeira shava, it says ונגאל v'nigaal means only
you redeem it all as one unit. So you can't do it
partially. אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so the גמרא Gemara seems to say,
okay, fine, whether גזרה שוה, gzeira shava, whether the language itself, you
won't do it partially. But that's not the end of the discussion.
אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אביי Abaye said, אם תמצא לומר נגאל לחציין,
im timtza lomar nigaal l'chetzyan, if you would say the opposite side,
like completely like ignoring the, like
not buying the conclusion of the previous גמרא, Gemara, if you would
say that you can redeem an עבד עברי eved Ivri part-way, משכחת
לה לקולא ולחומרא. mishkachat la l'kula ul'chumra. There are scenarios where that
would be lenient and scenarios where it would be strict. What's לקולא?
l'kula? זבניה במאה, zavnei b'meah, let's say you bought him with a
hundred. So they're, okay, יהיב ליה חמשין. yahaiv leh chamshin. And he
paid now off fifty, assuming let's say he paid at the beginning
of the six years of service. פלגא דדמי, palga d'damei, half of
the value. ואשבח, v'ashbach, and then again, assuming like no time elapsed
here, so we don't have to factor that in. Then the market
went up. Okay, וקם במאתן, v'kam b'maatan, and now he's worth two
hundred. אי אמרת נגאל לחציין, i amart nigaal l'chetzyan, if you would
say that you can pay off part, you know, in installment, part-way,
that he had already redeemed himself halfway, יהיב ליה מאה ונפיק, yahaiv
leh meah v'nafick, because he only has half of, he's already paid
half of his, bought back half of himself. So now he's worth
two hundred, but half has been paid for, he only has to
give another hundred. Okay, יהיב ליה מאה ונפיק, yahaiv leh meah v'nafick,
and he goes out. ואי אמרת אין נגאל לחציין, v'i amart ein
nigaal l'chetzyan, if the original payment of fifty was not meaningful, so
יהיב, yahaiv, so now he's worth two hundred, the fifty was a
deposit but it wasn't yet a buyback, so יהיב ליה מאה וחמשין
ונפיק. yahaiv leh meah v'chamshin v'nafick. He now has to pay the
full two hundred, so it's an additional hundred and fifty. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says, so that's the case where it would be
לקולא. l'kula. So the גמרא Gemara says, "One minute," says the גמרא,
Gemara, "I don't get
this." ואמרת נתרבה כספו מכסף מקנתו. v'amarta nisraba kaspo mikesef miknaso. So
the גמרא Gemara says you don't need in that scenario, okay, the
scenario is...
Okay.
January 1st, he was bought for a hundred dollars. What? Is this
thing go dead?
I'm trying to figure out how he's fifty from yesterday.
Well, that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara says, so you don't have
to figure it out. January 1st, he was bought for a hundred
dollars. On January 2nd, he did a payback of fifty dollars. Okay.
And now,
I'm... yes. On January 3rd, his value was two hundred dollars. Okay,
that's how much he was worth now, that's his value. Okay. So
what's, so? If you say that that was paid for half of
him, so then he only has a hundred dollars left because he
only has half of him left to buy back and he only
gives a hundred dollars. If this did not buy him back, he
has to pay, he has to buy himself back for the full
two hundred, so he pays fifty, it's an extra hundred and fifty.
That's what the גמרא Gemara says, right? But the גמרא Gemara says,
"One minute. Why do you need any of that?" We said as
Michael realized yesterday, that you always go by the lesser of the
purchase price and the current value. So even if this didn't work,
even if this was not a partial buyback, even if you just
came here and he wanted to buy himself back, he would only
have to give a hundred dollars. You go by the lesser, right?
Why are you paying attention to this two hundred? You always go
by the lesser. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says,
where were we?
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואמרת נתרבה כספו מכסף
מקנתו, v'amarta nisraba kaspo mikesef miknaso, if his value went up, you
go by the purchase price. So whatever, you don't need a partial
buyback, you're always going to go by a hundred here anyway. So
the גמרא Gemara says, "No." כגון דאוקיר וזל ואוקיר. kegon de'okar v'zal
v'okar. No, no, no, because what really happened was, was,
January 1st when he was bought, he was worth two hundred dollars.
On January 2nd,
when he bought himself back, his price had gone down to a
hundred. Now on January 3rd, his value was back up to two
hundred. Okay? It's like, you know, you buy, you know, GameStop... No,
so he gave the fifty on January 2nd. This guy said, "Oh,
great." My value has gone down, this is the perfect time to
buy myself back, cause I'm now only worth a hundred, it'll be
cheaper to buy myself back. And now you're at January 3. So
here, whether you go by the sale price or the current price,
it's 200. So if this didn't mean anything, the sale price was
200, the current price is 200, you need to pay 200. You've
already, like, whatever, deposited 50, but it hasn't been a, you haven't
paid yourself back, so you need an extra 150. But if here
you've bought half yourself back, then although the value, the price is
200, you only owe half of that and you only owe the
remaining 100, okay?
So they didn't have fixed rates and amortization?
Exactly, yeah, this was the whole mortgage עבד eved bubble that was
about to burst. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אם ניגאל
לחצאין ניגאל לחצאין.
im
niga l'chetzain niga l'chetzain.
Right, so you check yourself?
Yeah,
you wait till your value goes down. Right.
That's what you do. You start collecting money and then you're tracking
the market and as soon as it goes down a little bit,
you buy back some of yourself. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Now, מכחשו לחומרא, mikh'shu l'ḥumra, now the חומרא ḥumra
case is you can also find obviously that you made a bad
choice. Okay, דזבניה במאתן, dezavnai b'm'asan,
he was purchased for 200 and when it was still worth, he
was still worth 200, יהיב מאה, yahiv meah, פלגא דדמי, palga d'damei,
you paid off a hundred. ואיכסיף וקאי אמאה, v'ikhsif v'ka'amah meah,
and now you're only worth 100. So אי אמרת ניגאל לחצאין, i
amarta niga l'ḥetzain,
if that first 100 was an actual buyback, so you bought back
half yourself, so okay, you bought back half yourself. Now you're worth
100, so half of that you, if you wanted to buy back
the other half, you'd have to pay 50. יהיב ליה חמישין ונפיק.
yahiv lei khamishim v'nafek.
But you can't just say then, alright, I'm worth a hundred, I
paid a hundred, I'm free.
No, cause that was a, that was a sale at that time.
You bought back half yourself. That wasn't money, the money wasn't held
in escrow, that was a done deal, you bought back half yourself.
But ואי אמרת אין ניגאל לחצאין, v'i amarta ein niga l'ḥetzain, but
if there was no buyback that was doable at that time when
you paid the hundred, what did you do? You didn't buy yourself
back. So by giving the guy a hundred dollars, all you did
was, הנך מאה מאה פקדון נינהו, hanakh meah meah pikadon ninnu, you
just had him hold onto the hundred dollars for you. There was
no transaction that was possible. So אי איתנהו גביה, i ithanhu gabbeh,
יהיב ליה ונפיק, yahiv lei v'nafek,
so now he keeps the hundred dollars, now your value's a hundred
and let him keep the hundred dollars, okay? So whether you can
buy back part or not depends on how smart you are playing
the market. But the גמרא Gemara does not give the scenario like
רשי, Rashi, that if you could buy back yourself partway, that you
could actually cut down your length of service. Okay, but this is
anyway the question of the גמרא. Gemara. Do we say this or
not? So the גמרא Gemara has not resolved it.
And now, but wait, so wait, if you end up paying, what,
regardless of the שיטה, shita, if you end up buying yourself back,
you then still have to complete the terms of the service?
No. No, you buy yourself back and you go free. But רשי
Rashi says, but if you bought back half yourself, do you go
free with half, you reduce, got it.
So
are we saying if he gave a hundred dollars and then his
price went down to a hundred, he goes free?
If the original hundred dollars didn't count as a buyback. If the
original hundred dollars didn't count as a buyback, then he was just,
the master was just holding onto the hundred dollars for him. For
what purpose? I don't know, whatever, it was a mistake and the
master
was, give it back to me and here it is again and
then I go free. Exactly. But if it did count as a
buyback? If he said, this, I'm giving you a hundred towards my
redemption and then his price...
But if you say the הלכה halakha is אין ניגאל לחצאין, ein
niga l'ḥetzain, it didn't do anything at that time. It would just
essentially be held in escrow. That's all very nice, we'll put it
aside till you get all the money together. Okay? And therefore, since
it had not yet been effective, you can use the full amount
now to pay him to buy himself back.
No,
but what I'm asking is, if he gave him a hundred dollars
on account, right? And then on account for 200 and then his
price went down to 100, does he go free at that point?
It depends if you say ניגאל לחצאין. niga l'ḥetzain. Okay, he says,
here's a hundred dollars, I'm buying myself back. Okay, now, if that
worked, if ניגאל לחצאין, niga l'ḥetzain, then there was, the effect of
that was half your, half your debt has been paid off. If
אין ניגאל לחצאין, ein niga l'ḥetzain, that had no effect, it was
like, alright, I'll put this aside until you can get all the
rest of the money together. It's safe money. Right. And then since
it was only put aside, now that the market went down to
a hundred, now let's just use that hundred to buy myself back
fully. Okay, now, בעי מיניה רב הונא בר חיננא מרב ששת, be'ei
minei Rav Huna bar Hinena mei-Rav Sheshet, רב הונא בר חיננא Rav
Huna bar Hinena asked רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, המוכר בית בבתי ערי
חומה, ha-mokher bayit b'vatei arei homah, since we asked this about עבד
עברי, eved ivri, let's ask it by the other cases. Somebody sells
a house in a walled city. ניגאל לחצאין או אין ניגאל לחצאין?
niga l'ḥetzain o ein niga l'ḥetzain? Can you buy back halfway or
not? גאולתו גאולתו משדה אחוזה, ge'ulato ge'ulato mi-sdeh ahuzzah, again by שדה
אחוזה, sdeh ahuzzah, the ancestral field, it's כדי גאולתו, kedei ge'ulato, you
need the full amount. So therefore we should learn it out גמרא,
g'mara, you learn it out, מה שדה אחוזה אינה נגאלת לחצאין אף
האי נמי אינה נגאלת לחצאין. mah sdeh ahuzzah einah nig'elet l'ḥetzain af
hai nami einah nig'elet l'ḥetzain. So do we say the same way
by שדה אחוזה sdeh ahuzzah can't be halfway, this can't be halfway?
או דלמא, o dilma, or do we say, היכא דגלי גלי היכא
דלא גלי לא גלי. heikha d'gali gali heikha d'lo gali lo gali.
No, if it's not explicit here, that's not the law.
So therefore what would we say, the same question by a בית
בבתי ערי חומה bayit b'vatei arei homah where you have a year
to buy it back, if you can, can you buy it back
partially until and or or in stages or do you have to
buy it back all at once? אמר
ליה, Amar leih, מדרשא דרבי שמעון נשמע. Mi-drasha de-Rabbi Shimon nishma.
We can infer this from the דרשא drasha of רבי שמעון, Rebi
Shimon, שלווה וגואל וגואל לחצאין, she-loveh ve-goel ve-goel le-chetzayin, because there's another
question to be asked, not only can you buy back halfway, but
can you borrow money in order to buy back? Because the Torah
says by שדה אחוזה Sedei Achuzah two things. It says ונמצא כדי
גאולתו. ve-nimtza kedei geulato. So כדי גאולתו kedei geulato means the full
amount. ונמצא ve-nimtza means you managed to finally get collect that money,
get that money. Okay, and the way the one way the here
is דרשא drasha ונמצא פרט לשכבר מצוי, ve-nimtza perat le-she-kevar matzui, okay,
as opposed to if the money was already available. So, let's say
there's another scenario. Let's say for example, I actually had a car
that I could have sold, you know, but instead I sold my
שדה אחוזה. Sedei Achuzah. Okay, and now I'm going to sell my
car, get the money from the proceeds of the car and buy
back my שדה אחוזה. Sedei Achuzah. So, you're not allowed to do
that. Or you're not entitled to force the guy to sell you
back. This idea that you could be גואל, goel, you could buy
back against the will of the purchaser, that's only under certain conditions.
Okay, so and so if you actually had that money available to
you, you didn't want to sell your car but it doesn't matter
you had that asset, so that's not new money that you've just
discovered, okay, so then you're not entitled now to sell your car
and use that money to buy back. It's only money that you
did not have at that time. Similarly, okay, if I borrow money
to buy it back, that's not that I have now found that
money. It's like basically that's other people's money. Okay, that also doesn't
count. So your entitlement to buy back your שדה אחוזה Sedei Achuzah
against the will of the owner, A, you have to be כדי
גאולתו, kedei geulato, the full amount, and B, it has to be
money that you basically have recently come into. It's not other people's
money and it's not assets that you've already had. Okay, so that's
the
הלכה halacha of
שדה אחוזה. Sedei Achuzah. So the question is, is that true about
being גואל goel an עבד עברי, Eved Ivri, is it true about
being גואל goel a בית בבתי ערי חומה. Bayit be-batei arei chomah.
Okay, so let's take a look. Okay, so he says like
this: ממדרשא דרבי שמעון נשמע, Mi-drasha de-Rabbi Shimon nishma, שלווה וגואל וגואל
לחצאין. she-loveh ve-goel ve-goel le-chetzayin. So your question about בית בבתי ערי
חומה, Bayit be-batei arei chomah, we can learn it out from רבי
שמעון Rebi Shimon who says when it comes to that you can
borrow and redeem and you can redeem halfway, two separate הלכות. halachot.
דתניא: De-tanya: אם גאל יגאל איש, Im gaol yigal ish, אם גאל
יגאל, im gaol yigal, if you will redeem. Now this is talking
about redeeming from a fourth case, if this is not confusing enough,
a case where you sanctified your field. Okay, so, let's talk about
what we've got. We have שדה
אחוזה
Sedei
Achuzah where it
says ומצא כדי גאולתו. u-matza kedei geulato. כדי גאולתו kedei geulato means
the full amount and מצא matza is אינו לווה, eino loveh, you
don't borrow, okay, your own money. You can't borrow. Okay, that's what
you have by שדה אחוזה. Sedei Achuzah. Okay, the question we asked
is what's the story by עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. Right now we
don't know, okay, we had different ways of saying it out. Now
we want to know what's the story by what בית בבתי ערי
חומה, Bayit be-batei arei chomah, בית בערי חומה. Bayit be-arei chomah. Okay,
and also, it says גאולתו, geulato, right, do we make a גזירה
שוה gezeirah shavah or do we say we don't make a גזירה
שוה? gezeirah shavah? That's case number three. Case number four is מקדיש
שדה, makdish sadeh, okay, when you sanctify a field, if you don't
redeem it before the יובל, Yovel, it's going to go to the
כהנים. Kohanim. If you redeem it from the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
before the יובל, Yovel, you get it back, okay, and that says
ואם גאל יגאל, ve-im gaol yigal, גאל יגאל, gaol yigal, a double
language. ואם גאל יגאל. ve-im gaol yigal. So let's see what we're
going to say about מקדיש שדה makdish sadeh and whether what how
it plays out with this how it is similar or dissimilar from
the paradigm of שדה אחוזה. Sedei Achuzah. All right, דתניא, de-tanya, אם
גאל יגאל, im gaol yigal, מלמד שלווה וגואל וגואל לחצאין. melamed she-loveh
ve-goel ve-goel le-chetzayin. The double language means that you can when we're
giving you many opportunities to redeem. So this is different, I'll use
a different color, okay, this is different from the שדה אחוזה. Sedei
Achuzah. גאל יגאל gaol yigal says you can borrow, so much for
that, you can borrow and you can do it halfway, okay, the
exact opposite of this. The double language gives you more opportunities to
redeem. מלמד שלווה וגואל וגואל לחצאין. melamed she-loveh ve-goel ve-goel le-chetzayin. אמר
רבי שמעון, Amar Rebi Shimon, מה טעם, mah taam, what's the reason?
ולפי, U-lefi, now רבי שמעון Rebi Shimon is דורש טעמא דקרא, doresh
taama de-kra, so he finds a reason. לפי שמצינו במוכר שדה אחוזה
שיפה כחו lefi she-matzinu be-mocher sedei achuzah she-yafeh kocho because in the
case of שדה אחוזה Sedei Achuzah you have a lot of you,
the seller, have a lot of rights and a lot of strength.
What's the strength you have?
שאם הגיע יובל she-im higia Yovel In this case, what would happen
if you did not redeem it? Comes the יובל, yovel, you'd get
it back. So since anyway you're getting it back by the יובל,
yovel, the Torah does not have to make it harder for you
to get it back before the יובל. yovel. Like there are other
interests here. How about the guy who put out the money and
purchased it, right? What about him? We have to protect his interests
as well. So since you're getting it back anyway in the יובל,
yovel, he says, the Torah makes it hard to buy, to get
back beforehand.
מקדיש שדה Makdish sadeh is going to go to the כהנים Kohanim
ביובל. be-yovel. So since you're not going to get it back in
the יובל, yovel, the Torah makes it easier for you to get
it back beforehand. Very nice. Okay. ביובל הורע כוחו שאינו לוה וגואל
לחצאין. Be-yovel hura kocho she-eino loveh ve-go'el lachatzayin. So by שדה אחוזה
sadeh achuza you're gonna get it back, you're disadvantaged before that. מקדיש,
Makdish, by sanctifying שהורע כוחו, she-hura kocho, your power is weaker, שהגיע
יובל ולא נגאלה, she-higia yovel velo nig'ala, if it's not redeemed come
the יובל, yovel, יצא לכהנים ביובל, yetze la-kohanim be-yovel, it goes to
the כהנים, Kohanim, so יפה כוחו, yifeh kocho, so the Torah gives
you more power beforehand, שלוה וגואל לחצאין, she-loveh ve-go'el lachatzayin, that you
can borrow and you can do ever... all right, we'll get to
that. But this is how רב שמעון Rav Shimon understands it. Now,
hi... now we... that was very nice, but we were asking about
בתי ערי חומה. batei arei chomah. But the גמרא Gemara is saying
רב שמעון Rav Shimon gave us the logic. So now that we
know the logic, we can apply it to cases that we don't
know the הלכה. halakha.
Okay, בתי ערי חומה batei arei chomah you're more strict.
So let's take a look. Right? Exactly.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: now האי מוכר בבתי ערי
חומה נמי, hai mocher be-vatei arei chomah nami, so let's apply this
logic, הואיל והורע כוחו שמלאה לו שנה תמימה ולא נגאלה נחלט, ho'il
ve-hura kocho she-mal'ah lo shanah temimah velo nig'ala nechlat, right?
So therefore, what's the הלכה halakha by a house in a walled
city? If you don't buy it back in the first year, that's
it, you've totally lost it. You only have one year to buy
it back. So you have a very limited window. So according to
רב שמעון's Rav Shimon's logic, if you have a limited window, we
want to give you more opportunity. So what we're going to do
is we're going to say לוה וגואל, loveh ve-go'el,
יפה כוחו שלוה וגואל לחצאין. yifeh kocho she-loveh ve-go'el lachatzayin. Okay, very
nice. That's what you get by the way by דרשינן טעמא דקרא.
darshinan ta'ama de-kra. If you think you can get to the underlying
principle then you could apply it to cases that you don't know
what the הלכה halakha is. Okay, so here you lose it ביובל,
be-yovel, ביובל, be-yovel,
so you get this
special opportunity. Here you lose it after a year, lose it after,
right, a year, so that's bad, so we're going to give you
these special opportunities to buy back. That's how the גמרא Gemara has
tried to resolve it, okay, following רב שמעון. Rav Shimon. Let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. איתיבי, Eitivei, but I'll ask you on
this. We've got a ברייתא braita that says otherwise. אם גאל יגאל,
Im go'ol yigo'al,
again by מקדיש שדה, makdish sadeh, מלמד שלוה וגואל לחצאין, melamed she-loveh
ve-go'el lachatzayin,
so same הלכה. halakha. גאל יגאל Go'ol yigo'al tells you can get
those special opportunities. שיכול ולא דינו? She-yachol velo dino?
I might have made a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. ומה מוכר שדה
אחוזה שיפה כוחו, Uma mocher sedeh achuza she-yifeh kocho, by מוכר שדה
אחוזה mocher sedeh achuza you start off in a strong position, שהגיע
יובל ולא נגאלה חוזרת לבעלה ביובל, she-higia yovel velo nig'ala chozeret le-ba'ala
ba-yovel,
that you're going to get it back in the יובל, yovel,
and even so, this is the opposite logic of רב שמעון. Rav
Shimon. This is: if this is generally something that gives you... you
have a strong position in, you're going to get it back, logically
you should have other strengths as well, other opportunities as well. It's
strong, it's strong. Right? So therefore you would think that you would
have... if it's already strong you're going to get it back you
think you'd have these powers as well, this strength as well, and
nevertheless you don't. This that's generally weaker that you're going to lose
it, you certainly shouldn't have those powers. Okay, so so that's the
opposite argument of רב שמעון. Rav Shimon. לא חוזרת לבעלה ביובל, Lo
chozeret le-ba'ala ba-yovel, הורע כוחו שאינו לוה וגואל לחצאין, hura kocho she-eino
loveh ve-go'el lachatzayin,
so by שדה אחוזה sadeh achuza where you're generally strong, nevertheless you
don't have these opportunities, okay, מקדיש makdish by the case of מקדיש
makdish שהורע כוחו she-hura kocho that your position starts off as a
weak one, שאם הגיע יובל ולא נגאלה יצא לכהנים ביובל, she-im higia
yovel velo nig'ala yetze la-kohanim be-yovel, that if it's that it will
go to the כהנים Kohanim if you don't redeem it, אינו דין
שהורע כוחו, eino din she-hura kocho, how much more so should you
have the other weakness, שאינו לוה וגואל לחצאין, she-eino loveh ve-go'el lachatzayin,
that you're not able to borrow money, you're not able to redeem
it halfway? The exact opposite of רב שמעון. Rav Shimon. So anyway
the ברייתא braita continues, מה למוכר שדה אחוזה, ma le-mocher sedeh achuza,
no
no no, one minute. The case of שדה אחוזה sedeh achuza שכן
הורע כוחו לגאול מיד. she-ken hura kocho lig'ol mi-yad.
Following your logic that it's either all bad or all good, I
will go tell you that the case of שדה אחוזה sedeh achuza
is a weak category. It's true you get it back ביובל, be-yovel,
but why is it weak? It's weak because you have to... you
can't buy it back in the first two years. By the case
of מקדיש שדה, makdish sadeh, you're entitled to buy it back immediately.
So therefore maybe this is the stronger one and maybe therefore logically
you would have those opportunities. Now you do have these opportunities but
the question is why do we need a פסוק? pasuk? Could we
have figured it out logically? Okay, so מה למוכר שדה אחוזה שכן
הורע כוחו לגאול מיד, ma le-mocher sedeh achuza she-ken hura kocho lig'ol
mi-yad, תאמר במקדיש שיפה כוחו, tomar be-makdish she-yifeh kocho, by מקדיש שדה
makdish sadeh it's a stronger case, לגאול מיד. lig'ol mi-yad. So in
that case I might have said I don't need a פסוק, pasuk,
logically I'd say this is stronger and you have these opportunities. So
wait wait wait, מוכר בבתי ערי חומה יוכיח. mocher be-vatei arei chomah
yokhi'ach. No no no, let's figure out from the case of
בתי ערי batei arei and
nevertheless ואין לו וגאולה וגאולה לחצאים. ve'ein lo u'geulah u'geulah lachatzayim. This
ברייתא braita assumes that you don't have these opportunities, okay? According to
this ברייתא, braita, it has to be your own money and it
has to be full. According to this ברייתא, braita, okay? So here
you have the ability to buy back and you don't have those
opportunities, and here, right, so here too, right, just because you have
the opportunity to buy back and it's stronger that way, this shows
you that it does not give you these opportunities. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says ואין לו וגאולה וגאולה לחצאים. ve'ein lo u'geulah
u'geulah lachatzayim. Now, so basically the way this ברייתא braita structures it,
it says look, it says, well, by logic no, but the הלכה
halacha is the same about מקדיש. makdish. מקדיש Makdish tells me גאול
יגאל gaol yigal that it has these special powers, special privileges: you
can borrow and you can do it halfway. Okay. But it's saying
I would not have known that logically because they have two other
cases where you don't have those privileges. Okay, even though this is
strong that you get it back ביובל, beyovel, you don't have those
privileges. Even though this is strong that you buy it back in
the first year, you don't have those privileges. So this which is
weaker than those things, logically you shouldn't have those privileges but the
פסוק pasuk teaches me you do. Okay. Now, but the point is
this clearly is not רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, right? Because
clearly the logic was the opposite of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. The
logic here was all stronger all weak, as opposed to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon which was a counterbalancing logic. Because it's strong here, we
have to make it weak here, you know? It's clearly a counter-רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon argument. But our question about בתי ערי חומה batei
arei choma according to this ברייתא braita is that you don't have
those privileges. But we argued according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, since
this is a weak category, you should have those privileges. So the
גמרא Gemara says fine, לא קשיא, lo kashya, הא רבנן הא רבי
שמעון. ha rabanan ha Rabbi Shimon. Good, okay, it's not a problem,
you're right. This ברייתא braita reflects a רבנן Rabanan approach, which is
strong goes with strong, weak goes with weak. And according to this
you don't have those privileges because this is a weak category. But
if we adopt רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, which I think to us
makes a little bit more sense, or I'll just say whatever, then
we'll say no, it's a counterbalancing argument. So in בתי ערי חומה,
batei arei choma, because it's so weak, that's why you do have
those privileges according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Yes.
So two things: one, you would say correct that according to רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's logic is not a formalistic
קל וחומר kal v'chomer logic, it's a, it's sort of an ethical,
okay, right. And is this unusual for a ברייתא braita to have
such a שקלא וטריא? shakla v'tarya?
No, that's very classic in מדרשי הלכה. midreshei halacha. The מדרשי הלכה,
midreshei halacha, that's actually a classic structure. It says here's what we
learned from the פסוק, pasuk, then it says והלא דין הוא, vehalo
din hu, you didn't need it from a פסוק, pasuk, you could
have learned it out logically, and it goes through the whole thing
and shows why you could not have concluded logically and that's why
you needed the פסוק.
pasuk. I mean that was why I'm asking, well, do you still
call a מדרש הלכה midrash halacha a ברייתא? braita?
Yeah, the גמרא Gemara when it quotes מדרש הלכה midrash halacha says
תניא. tanya. It doesn't have another word for מדרש הלכה. midrash halacha.
Oh, yeah.
So first of all I was looking this up, where does it
say שדה אחוזה Sadeh Achuza means your own money in this? Like
did I miss this in the גמרא? Gemara?
No, the גמרא Gemara was just assuming it, that, I mean that
דרשה drasha was not stated explicitly, I mean I think it's elsewhere
in רמב"ם Rambam quotes it or whatever, but okay.
And the other thing is does it say the word גאולתו geulato
in בתי ערי חומה? batei arei choma? Does it say גאולתו? geulato?
Or did you just write that there, you put it in quotes?
It says גאולתו, geulato, why wouldn't you just,
no it says it, that was גמרא'ס Gemara's question. Right, the גמרא'ס
Gemara's question was do we say גאולתו geulato means the
word... בתי
ערי חומה גאולתו משדה אחוזה, batei arei choma geulato mi'Sadeh Achuza, blah
blah blah.
Right, but then meaning, but to me it just seems like, I
guess, you know, if, I mean they just didn't have this מסורה
mesorah because it says גאולתו geulato in שדה אחוזה, Sadeh Achuza, it
says גאולתו geulato in
בתי ערי חומה, batei arei choma, there it says גאול יגאל, gaol
yigal, a slightly different word that I would think...
that's exactly what the question was. But the argument... I understand, but
that's the power of רבי שמעון דורשין טעמא דקרא. Rabbi Shimon dorshin
ta'ama dikra. He's more interested in the underlying logic than in some
structure than in some language similarity.
You have a גזירה שוה,
gzera shava, you don't do that because... well, according to רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, I mean again I don't know if it's an ironclad
rule but that's רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's power of דורשין טעמא דקרא.
dorshin ta'ama dikra. He's more interested in the underlying logic dictating rather
than the similarity of those words. Now I'm not saying that's a
hundred percent, but that's, yeah.
So the opinion is you can buy in halves, so what happens
when the יובל yovel comes and you've only paid half?
Yeah, so that's a good question. So that goes back to רש"י'ס
Rashi's question about buying back half of your servant. According to רש"י,
Rashi, would you get back half of your field? I don't know.
Maybe the point would be you'd get back your money. Buying back
half gives you this ability to buy it back in an advantageous
way, but at the end of the day maybe if you didn't
have it all bought back when יובל yovel came you might lose
out. It's not clear from the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. I mean presumably
you get back your money but you know. Okay. Now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, תני חדא tani chada לוה וגואל וגואל לחצאין.
loveh ve'goel ve'goel lachatzayin. Now back to the בתי ערי חומה. batei
arei choma. One ברייתא braita says you can borrow money and do
it halfway, ותניא אידך vetanya idach אין לוה וגואל וגואל לחצאין, ein
loveh ve'goel ve'goel lachatzayin, you can't. And now we already know the
answer. לא קשיא, lo kashya, הא רבנן הא רבי שמעון. ha rabanan
ha Rabbi Shimon. According to the Rabbis, weak goes with weak, so
you don't have those powers. According to רבי שמעון, Rabi Shimon, strong
goes with weak, you want to counterbalance. So בית בבתי ערי חומה,
bayit b'batei arei chomah, which is a weak position, you counterbalance it
and you give him the rights of buy back halfways and borrowing
the money. Okay, אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי, amar
lei Rav Acha Brei De'Rava le'Rav Ashi, איכא למיפרך, ika l'mifrach, one
minute, I got a question going back on that קל וחומר kal
v'chomer in the ברייתא. baraita. Okay, we're trying to say could you
have learned out, you know, from here without the פסוק. pasuk. So
here's the question: מה למוכר בית בבתי
ערי חומה שכן הורע כוחו לגאול לעולם, mah l'mocher bayit b'batei arei
chomah she'ken hura kocho l'goel l'Olam, תאמר במקדיש שיפה כוחו לגאול לעולם.
tomar b'makdish she'yafa kocho l'goel l'Olam. Okay, so now we're getting confusing,
okay, as if it weren't confusing yet. So back to what we
were saying, according to the ברייתא baraita that assumed that this could
only be own and full, okay, it was saying that look, this,
these two cases show you that even though they're strong, okay, this
is strong because you get back in the יובל, Yovel, this is
strong first year, nevertheless you have this weakness associated. So certainly this
you should have the weakness associated. That was what the ברייתא baraita
said. So he said wait a minute. מה למוכר בית בבתי ערי
חומה שכן הורע כוחו לגאול לעולם. mah l'mocher bayit b'batei arei chomah
she'ken hura kocho l'goel l'Olam. This
is not strong. It's true you can buy this back in one
year, okay, one year buyback, okay, but it's really a very weak
category. Why is this a very weak category? Because after one year
you can never, never buy back, okay, after one year, after you
can never buy back, right? So if you, so this category, you're
saying oh it's a strong category and nevertheless it has this weakness.
This is not a strong category. בית בערי חומה bayit b'arei chomah
is a very weak category because after one year you can never
buy back. What's the הלכה halakha about מקדיש שדה? makdish sadeh? You
can always buy back.
How's that? How can you always buy back?
Until whatever, until the יובל, Yovel, until the יובל. Yovel. You can
always buy back. So don't tell me, I'm still going to say
that these categories are weak. This is weak because you could never
buy back, right? This is weak because you can't buy back even
during the first year. And this is very strong. You could buy
back in year one, you could buy back from year one to
the יובל. Yovel. Here let's just do it this way. Here the
buyback period is year one to the יובל. Yovel. Here the buyback
period is year one. Here the buyback period is year three to
the יובל. Yovel. So just look at the buyback periods. This has
the biggest buyback period, from year one up to the יובל. Yovel.
So okay, you have a weakness here, you've got a weakness here
because both of these have limited buyback periods. This only starts in
year three, this only is year one. This has the biggest buyback
period. So why do, why don't I need a פסוק pasuk to
tell this to me, אם גאול יגאל, im gaol yigaol, that this
has these powers? I should just know that because it's stronger than
the other two.
What happens if you're מקדיש makdish your שדה sadeh for that, it
just lays fallow for that period?
No, the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash could use it and make income
off of it. Ah, the house of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
Yeah, and they'll have
flocks there and plant or whatever. Okay, so מה למוכר בית בבתי
ערי חומה שכן הורע כוחו לגאול לעולם, mah l'mocher bayit b'batei arei
chomah she'ken hura kocho l'goel l'Olam, by the walled city you can't
buy back forever, תאמר במקדיש שיפה כוחו לגאול לעולם. tomar b'makdish she'yafa
kocho l'goel l'Olam. So the case of מקדיש, makdish, that is a
stronger category than the other two. And therefore why did I need
a פסוק pasuk to tell me it has this power of halfway
and borrowing, okay, I should just know that because it's stronger than
the other two. אמר ליה רב אחא סבא לרב אשי, amar lei
Rav Acha Sava le'Rav Ashi, משום דאיכא למימר, mishum d'ika l'meimar, ניהדר
דינא ותיתי ממה הצד, nihadar dina ve'teiti mi'ma'atzad, because we're going to
go through look at all the three categories, go back to the
other case. מוכר שדה אחוזה יוכיח mocher sdeh achuzah yochiach שכן יפה
כוחו לגאול לעולם. she'ken yafa kocho l'goel l'Olam. Now I sort of
a little bit jumped to the end of the
גמרא. Gemara. No, you can't say that this is weak, this is
weak because it can't be redeemed forever, okay, because, because it can't
be redeemed after year one. Because this can be redeemed for a
long period of time and so and you know so this I
so now I'm losing my track. This is hard. Okay, the argument
is is that, you know, what we want to prove is is
that
it's not a particular weakness that leads to this הלכה. halakha. Right
again, this is the assumption that weak goes with weak. So the
argument is well each of these have a weakness, these are weak
and that's why they have this הלכה. halakha. So the answer is
wait a minute, it's not weak. What's weak about this? What's weak
about בית בבתי ערי חומה bayit b'batei arei chomah is is that
it can't be redeemed after year one. But this can be redeemed
after year one. So that clearly doesn't count and it still has
this הלכה. halakha. So clearly it's not that weakness that that is
a tree that is the reason for this
הלכה. halakha. Ah, this has a different weakness. It can't be redeemed
immediately. Okay, that's the reason for the הלכה. halakha. Oh, but one
minute, this can, this can be redeemed immediately and and you still
have the הלכה. halakha. So the weakness of the weakness of, right,
the weakness of, you know, not, you know, not immediate, right, that's
the weakness of שדה אחוזה. sdeh achuzah. Okay, it has that weakness,
and so maybe that's why it has the הלכה Halakha of it
has to be whole, the הלכה Halakha here is all and your
own money,
okay? So that's the שדה אחוזה. S'de Achuza. That has the case
of not immediate. The weakness of not after year one,
not after year one, that's the case of the בתי ערי חומה
Batei Arei Choma and that has that הלכה. Halakha. But the argument
is, but but it's near, you can't attribute this הלכה Halakha to
either weakness because this weakness doesn't exist in this case and this
weakness doesn't exist in that case.
So you have to evaluate that they are of the same quality.
Right. So the assumption is this הלכה, Halakha, if you wanted to
limit it because of a particular weakness, it's not the same weakness
in either case. Okay. So.
Does that make it a weaker argument that it's not the same
weakness?
Yeah, well there's always the question of wanting to just say it
has some weakness, but the גמרא Gemara is going to get to
a better point which is sort of the point I had early,
I have to hedge here.
Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. מה למכור שדה אחוזה שכן אין כוחו
לגאול עולמית? Ma lemokher S'de Achuza sheken ein kocho ligoal olamit? Look,
it can't be the weakness that you can't do it forever, that
that's the weakness that attributes to this הלכה, Halakha, because מוכר שדה
אחוזה mokher S'de Achuza you can, you can buy it back until
the יובל Yovel and it still has this הלכה. Halakha. Ah, but
that has a different weakness. מה למכור שדה אחוזה שכן אין כוחו
לגאול מיד? Ma lemokher S'de Achuza sheken ein kocho ligoal miyad? You
can't buy back right away. Maybe that's the reason that שדה אחוזה
S'de Achuza has this הלכה. Halakha. No, that can't be the reason
for this הלכה Halakha because מוכר בתי ערי חומה יוכיח, mokher Batei
Arei Choma yokhiach, the case of the walled city shows that even
though you can buy it back right away, it has this הלכה.
Halakha. So the הלכה Halakha cannot be based on the fact that
you can't buy it back right away, and the הלכה Halakha cannot
be based on the fact that you don't have until the יובל.
Yovel. וחזר הדין, Vechazar Hadin, and it goes back and forth. לא
ראי זה כראי זה, Lo re'i zeh kire'i zeh, that each one's
unique qualities are not like the other one. הצד השוה שבהן, Hatzad
hashaveh shebahen, the common denominator is שמנגאלין, shenig'alin, that things that can
be, that whenever it's in the פרשה Parsha of things that are
redeemed, ואין לוה וגואל וגואל לחצאין, v'ein loveh vegoel vegoel lachatza'in, maybe
this is just a generic הלכה Halakha that all these cases of
forced redemption cannot be with borrowed money and cannot be halfway. אף
אני אביא מקדיש שמנגאל ואין לוה וגואל וגואל לחצאין. Af ani avi
makdish shenig'al v'ein loveh vegoel vegoel lachatza'in.
I would say the same here that so basically because each of
these have their own distinct categories and they both have the הלכה
Halakha that they can't be borrowed money and they can't be halfway,
I I would have said the same in case of מקדיש שדה.
makdish sadeh. But we don't, that's why all this is to explain
that's why you needed the פסוק. Pasuk. Okay, so now we've reestablished
the ברייתא Braitta why you needed the פסוק. Pasuk. But we're not
done. Why we're not done? Because it says like this. אמר ליה
מר זוטרא בריה דרב מרי לרבינא, Amar lei Mar Zutra berei de'Rav
Mari l'Ravina, no, איכא למפרך, ika lemifrach, I still can tell you
why I don't need the פסוק, Pasuk, and this is what I
was jumping to beforehand. מה להצד השוה שבהן שכן אין כוחו לגאול
בשנה שניה? Ma lehatzad hashaveh shebahen sheken ein kocho ligoal beshana shniya?
Neither of these can be redeemed in year two, right? This is
from year three to the יובל, Yovel, this is only year one,
neither of them can be redeemed in year two, which is a
way of saying that both of these have shorter redemption periods than
this. This has the entire period as a redemption period. So why
did you need a פסוק? Pasuk? The הלכה, Halakha, the weaknesses here
are because both of these have short redemption periods, or, and that's
actually even more specific, neither of these can be redeemed in year
two. It's too late for this and too early for that. So
this one which can be redeemed in year two, which has the
entire period as a redemption period, you wouldn't need a פסוק. Pasuk.
Logically you should have that strength. Okay. שבהן לגאול בשנה שניה. Shebahen
ligoal beshana shniya. תאמר במקדיש שיפה כוחו לגאול בשנה שניה? Tomar bemakdish
sheyafe kocho ligoal beshana shniya? אמר ליה רבינא, Amar lei Ravina, no,
משום דאיכא למימר, mishum d'ika lemeimar, oy, sorry, עבד עברי יוכיח, Eved
Ivri yokhiach, עכו"ם, Akum, ונמכר לו לעובד כוכבים יוכיח. Venimkar lo le'oved
kokhavim yokhiach.
No,
because we have another case, an עבד עברי Eved Ivri sold to
a non-Jew,
which is what our question was to begin with, whether an עבד
עברי Eved Ivri is נגאל לחצאין. nigaal lachatza'in. שיפה כוחו לגאול בשנה
שניה. Sheyafe kocho ligoal beshana shniya. An
עבד עברי Eved Ivri sold to a non-Jew can be redeemed from
the beginning, at the same time, like this, from the beginning of
sale till the יובל, Yovel, and we're going to assume that the
הלכה Halakha there is,
okay, ואין לוה וגואל וגואל לחצאין. v'ein loveh vegoel vegoel lachatza'in. We're
going to assume the הלכה Halakha is that it cannot be halfway
like we were discussing earlier. So therefore, this can't be halfway, this
can't be halfway, עבד עברי Eved Ivri according to this assumption also
is owned and the full amount, because of whatever, the גמרא Gemara
had a גזירה שוה gzera shava before, it was according to one
לימוד limud before. All of these can only be the owned and
the full amount of your own money and the full amount, and
no particular cannot be attributed to any particular weakness
because עבד עברי Eved Ivri is from year one to the יובל,
Yovel, okay,
well
no, because it's six years.
Whatever, the entire length. Okay, so it can't be attributed to any
weakness. So logically this should have been in the same category, and
that's why you needed the פסוק Pasuk אם גאל יגאל im gaol
yigal to tell you that the exception is
מקדיש שדה. makdish sadeh. neither of these can be redeemed. Okay, neither
of these can be
redeemed. So
there, okay, alright fine, we are done with that, ברוך השם. Baruch
Hashem. Okay, בעי מיני רב הונא בר חיננא מרב ששת. Ba'ei minei
Rav Huna bar Chinana me-Rav Sheshes. A lot of these questions, okay
no, a lot of these were בעי מיני רב הונא בר חיננא
מרב ששת Ba'ei minei Rav Huna bar Chinana me-Rav Sheshes as this
series of questions. I'm sorry, we're way behind. Okay, you ask, okay
so the question is to ask, בעי מיני רב הונא בר חיננא
מרב ששת: Ba'ei minei Rav Huna bar Chinana me-Rav Sheshes: המוכר בית
בבתי ערי חומה, Ha-mocher bayit be-vattei arei chomah, נגאל לקרובים nigg'al likrovim
או אין נגאל לקרובים? o ein nigg'al likrovim? Now that we're done
with halfway and borrowed money, here's another question.
Okay, the תורה, Torah, this is an easier question to focus on
because it's a simple question about פשט pshat of the reading of
the פסוקים. psukim. Okay, the פסוקים psukim only talk about this principle
that a relative can buy back
in two cases: שדה אחוזה Sadeh Achuzah and עבד עברי Eved Ivri
sold to a non-Jew. It does not talk about it in the
cases of a house in an עיר חומה ir chomah or an
עבד עברי Eved Ivri sold to a Jew. Okay, big questions. Now,
there's two aspects to the relatives buying back. One is it creates
a possible mandate on the relative to buy back, a מצוה חובה,
mitzvah chovah, we'll see about that in a minute, maybe not, right
maybe it's only רשות, reshus, but maybe it's an obligation. And number
two, the more primary one the גמרא Gemara is focusing on, is
that the purchaser is forced to accept the money and to allow
the person to go free. Okay, and that's הלכה halakhah about now
if somebody who wasn't a relative came and said, I'm buying back
this עבד עברי, Eved Ivri, I'm buying back this שדה אחוזה Sadeh
Achuzah for so and so, the guy could say no, sorry Charlie,
but if it's a relative, he has to accept it and it's
binding. So the question is in the תורה Torah that's again by
a שדה אחוזה Sadeh Achuzah and עבד עברי Eved Ivri who is
sold to a non-Jew. What about all the other cases? So let's
take a look.
If the addition says he'd be forced to sell it back,
it ameliorates the sense of ownership, it's like something interesting, you don't
really own it.
Right, well that's a good point, like yeah I mean you're right
and that's part of כי לי כל הארץ Ki li kol ha-aretz
and that's כי לי בני ישראל עבדים, Ki li bnei Yisrael avadim,
you know all of that.
Right, what do you think? Oh sure, well there are other cases?
Right, whether it applies to בתי ערי חומה, battei arei chomah,
I thought the whole point is if it's in one case it
might be a paradigm, so in all cases, one of these two
cases, alright
well let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, בעי מיני רב
הונא בר חיננא מרב ששת: Ba'ei minei Rav Huna bar Chinana me-Rav
Sheshes: המוכר בית בבתי ערי חומה, Ha-mocher bayit be-vattei arei chomah, נגאל
לקרובים? nigg'al likrovim? So in the case that it's a house in
a walled city. Is it redeemed by relatives or אין נגאל לקרובים?
ein nigg'al likrovim? גאולתו גאולתו משדה אחוזה גמר, Ge'ulato ge'ulato mi-sadeh achuzah
gamar, do you make a גזירה שוה: gezeirah shavah: גאולתו גאולתו? ge'ulato
ge'ulato? מה שדה אחוזה אינה נגאלת לחצאין ונגאלת לקרובים, Mah sadeh achuzah
einah nigg'eles lachatza'in ve-nigg'eles likrovim, okay
it's true that it's not done halfway, which we just got through
talking about, but it is redeemed by relatives. אף האי נמי אינה
נגאלת לחצאין ונגאלת לקרובים. Af hai nami einah nigg'eles lachatza'in ve-nigg'eles likrovim.
What?
ערי חומה. Arei chomah.
שדה אחוזה Sadeh Achuzah is by relatives, that's in the פסוקים, psukim,
and it's not halfway. This too we would say it's not halfway,
but it is by קרובים. krovim. או דלמא כי כתיב גאולה בחצאין
הוא דכתיב. O dilma ki ksiva ge'ulah be-chatza'in hu d'ksiva. No, maybe
the גזירה שוה: gezeirah shavah: גאולתו גאולתו, ge'ulato ge'ulato, right
is to tell you like we said, you were asking why do
we know
this הלכה halakhah that it's like this, that it has to be
your own money and it has to be the full amount, that's
because it says כדי גאולתו, kedei ge'ulato, that's exactly the word of
the full amount of the redemption. So maybe it's only to tell
you this link but not to tell you the קרובים krovim question.
Okay maybe קרובים krovim doesn't work. או דלמא כי כתיב בחצאין הוא
דכתיב בקרובים לא כתיב, O dilma ki ksiva be-chatza'in hu d'ksiva be-krovim
lo ksiva, maybe the קרובים krovim cannot do it by a house
in ערי חומה. arei chomah. אמר ליה אינו נגאל. Amar lei einu
nigg'al.
Yeah, it's not redeemed. You're right, there's no פסוק pasuk that tells
you it's done by קרובים, krovim, it can't be done by קרובים.
krovim. איתיבי, Eisivei, I'll ask you on this: ובכל גאולה תתנו. u-vekhol
ge'ulah titnu.
The פסוק pasuk is ובכל ארץ אחוזתכם גאולה תתנו לארץ. u-vekhol eretz
achuzat'khem ge'ulah titnu la-aretz.
But that's a very nice broad theological statement, but of course the
גמרא's Gemara like what new הלכה halakhah is that telling us? Like
all the הלכות halakhot of גאולה ge'ulah are written in the פסוקים.
psukim. What is the meaning of oh in everything give a גאולה?
ge'ulah? So ובכל גאולה תתנו, u-vekhol ge'ulah titnu, what does that teach
you?
So לרבות בתים ועבד עברי, le-rabot battim ve-eved ivri, to include houses
and עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. Now include them in what הלכה? halakhah?
What הלכה halakhah are they not included in? So the most obvious
thing to say is the הלכה halakhah of גאולה ge'ulah by קרובים.
krovim. קרובים Krovim is mentioned by שדה אחוזה, sadeh achuzah, it's mentioned
by an עבד עברי Eved Ivri sold to a non-Jew. And if
you have a broad statement there should be redemption about everything, it
will tell me that קרובים krovim can buy back even a house
in ערי חומה arei chomah and even עבד עברי Eved Ivri sold
to a Jew.
Like a פרט וכלל? prat u-khlal?
Or more just the כלל? klal? Okay yeah. Okay so מאי לאו
בתי Mai lav batin, ערי חומה? בתי ערי חומה battei arei chomah?
and can be bought back by קרובים. krovim. לא בתי חצר. Lo,
battei khatzer. No no no, it means houses that are in the
unwalled cities. בתי חצר בהדיא כתיבו, Battei khatzer be-hedya ksivu, you don't
need a פסוק, pasuk, and this פסוק, pasuk, that's an explicit פסוק.
pasuk. על שדי הארץ יחשב, Al sadei ha-aretz yekhashev, the פסוק pasuk
says that houses in unwalled cities are like fields. So if you
can redeem fields by קרובים, krovim, you can redeem houses in unwalled
cities by קרובים. krovim. So you don't need this generic inclusive פסוק
pasuk to refer to that. So the גמרא Gemara says no, ההוא
לכל החובה. hahu le-khol hakhovah. You're right, it's not merely needed to
tell you you know the idea of houses in unwalled cities. but
it's really needed to do, it's repeating בכל גאולה תתנו bechol gueila
titnu to tell you that the קרובים kroivim have an obligation to
redeem, not just a right to redeem, but an obligation to redeem.
Right, in those two cases they have an obligation to redeem. וקסבר
חובה v'kasvar chova ואליבא דרבי אליעזר v'aliba d'Rabbi Eliezer like Rabbi Eliezer.
Now we're going to get into another question which is, is it
just a right that the קרובים kroivim have or an obligation? דתניא,
dtanya, וגאל את ממכר אחיו v'ga'al et mimchar achiv and he will
redeem his brother's sale, רשות reshut he has the right to do
it. אתה אומר רשות או אינו אלא חובה ata omer reshut o
eino ela chova maybe he has an obligation? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar,
ואיש כי לא יהיה לו גואל v'ish ki lo yihiyeh lo go'el
if a man doesn't have a redeemer, then if he collects his
own money he can redeem it, ומצא כדי גאולתו umatzah k'dei gueulato
right, that's that פסוק posuk we've been quoting. He finds the money
to redeem. Okay, so what does it mean he doesn't have a
redeemer? וכי יש אדם בישראל שאין לו גואלים? v'chi yesh adam b'Yisrael
she'ein lo go'alim? Is there anybody that? Everybody has a relative. Okay,
so one answer is a גר ger but that's not the answer
we're giving now. אלא, ela, so what does it mean he has
no redeemer? זה שיש לו ואינו רוצה ליקח. zeh sheyesh lo v'eino
rotzeh likach. It means he doesn't have a redeemer means nobody's stepping
up to the plate. It doesn't mean he doesn't have a relative.
It means no relative
is you know stepping up and being willing to redeem. So what
the פסוק posuk is telling you is, oh if none of your
relatives want to redeem, then you can still redeem yourself. But what
does that show you? It shows you that the relatives can choose
to not redeem.
It's רשות. reshut. This is how we're learning רשות. reshut.
Okay, so שהרשות בידו דברי רבי יהושע. shehareshut biyado divrei Rabbi Yehoshua.
So the פסוק posuk is telling you what happens if a relative
doesn't want to, which shows you that relatives have the right to
say that they're not going to redeem. They have the right to
do it but they don't have the obligation to do it. Okay,
that's what Rabbi Yehoshua says. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, וגאל
את ממכר אחיו, v'ga'al et mimchar achiv, no no no. The פסוק
posuk that says and he shall redeem is to tell you חובה,
chova, it's an
obligation. אתה אומר חובה או אינו אלא רשות, ata omer chova o
eino ela reshut, maybe it means he has the right? תלמוד לומר,
talmud lomar, בכל גאולה תתנו, bechol gueila titnu, in the whole land,
in everything there should be redemption, הכתוב קבעו חובה. hakatuv kva'o chova.
So it's not to extend the scope, but to extend the obligation.
So what's the reason for doing it by רשות reshut and by?
Okay, well that's what the גמרא, Gemara, yeah I mean okay that's
a good question but I can't get into that now. I mean
you're right, why not just redeem it and have somebody buy back
from you? Okay, I understand. אמרי ליה רבנן לרב אשי, amri lei
rabanan l'Rav Ashi, so the rabbis said to Rav Ashi. Okay so
now we have not resolved the question of whether it applies to
בתי ערי חומה. Battei arei chomah We're saying the repetition of בכל
גאולה תתנו bechol gueila titnu is really just to tell me that
it's an obligation. Okay. אמרי ליה רבנן לרב אשי, amri lei rabanan
l'Rav Ashi, the rabbis said to Rav Ashi, ואמרי ליה רבינא לרב
אשי, v'amri lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi, and some say it was Ravina.
בשלמא למאן דאמר לרבות בתי ערי חומה, bishlama l'man d'amar lerabot batei
arei choma, if you say בכל גאולה תתנו bechol gueila titnu is
to tell you that the relatives redeem a house in a walled
city, היינו דכתיב בכל, hainu d'chtiv bechol, everything, which extends the scope
of it, right, the broad scope. אלא למאן דאמר לרבות בתי חצרים,
ela l'man d'amar lerabot batei chatzerim, but if it's to include houses
in the fields, which really doesn't mean to extend the scope, but
it really just means to repeat it for the sake of making
it an obligation, so מאי בכל? mai bechol? What's the word בכל?
bechol? בכל bechol seems to be a broader scope, and you're telling
me not a broader scope, just a deeper obligation. קשיא. kashya. All
right you're right, that's a problem. All right move on. איבעיא להו.
iba'ya l'hu. Okay so now we're still not done with this question
about whether it applies to בתי ערי חומה. batei arei choma. תא
מה תלמוד לומר, ta mah talmud lomar, יגאלנו יגאלנו יגאלנו yigalenu yigalenu
yigalenu ג' פעמים? gimel pe'amim? The ברייתא Beraita says right, או דודו
או בן דודו יגאלנו o dodo o ben dodo yigalenu או משאר
בשרו יגאלנו o mish'ar besaro yigalenu או השיגה ידו ונגאל. o hisiga
yado v'nig'al. Why does it keep on saying redeem, redeem, redeem? And
all those things about those פסוקים p'sukim are by a case of
buying back a Jew who sold
himself to a non-Jew. Okay, so why does it say it three
times? לרבות כל הגאולות שנגאלו כסדר הזה. lerabot kol hagueulot shenig'alu k'seder
hazeh. All redemptions are done like this. So what we assume that
means is that all other categories can be redeemed by relatives. Again,
the two unspecified categories are house in a walled city and עבד
עברי eved Ivri sold to a Jew. Okay, מאי לאו, mai lav
בתי ערי חומה ועבד עברי? batei arei choma v'eved Ivri? So it's
coming again to broaden the scope? לא, בתי חצרים ושדה אחוזה. Lo,
Batei Chatzerim veSdeh Achuzah. No no no, we just mean you know
the other thing that's explicit can be redeemed by relatives, which is
the fields and the houses in the unwalled cities. So the גמרא
Gemara says בתי חצרים ושדה אחוזה בהדיא כתיב. batei chatzerim v'sadeh achuza
behidya ktiv. על שדי הארץ יחשב. al s'dei ha'aretz yechashev. You don't
need יגאלנו יגאלנו יגאלנו. yigalenu yigalenu yigalenu. The פסוק posuk says that
those can be redeemed by relatives. שדה אחוזה sadeh achuza is explicit
and בתי חצרים batei chatzerim are like שדה אחוזה. sadeh achuza. So
what do you need יגאלנו yigalenu if you're only applying it to
the things we already know? So כדי אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק,
kide'amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, לקרוב קרוב קודם, l'karov karov kodem, הכא
נמי לקרוב קרוב קודם. hacha nami l'karov karov kodem. No, because the
פסוק posuk says by שדה אחוזה, sadeh achuza, it says הקרוב אליו
יגאלנו, hakrov elav yigalenu, but it does not tell you what the
order of relatives are. By the case of the Jew selling himself
to the non-Jew it says או דודו או בן דודו יגאלנו, o
dodo o ben dodo yigalenu, right, it sort of creates an order
in which the relatives redeem. So again, similar to what we said
before, the גמרא Gemara is saying this word of יגאלנו yigalenu is
not coming to extend the scope, the scope is limited... עבד עברי
Eved Ivri that's נמכר nimkar to a non-Jew and שדה אחוזה, Sdeh
Achuzah, but what it's coming to do is to tell you the
order in which the redemption gets done. What are the order in
which the relatives redeem? Who is the closer relative? Okay, so two
things sounded like they were extending the scope. The answer is no.
One of them is not extending the scope, it's just telling you
it's not a right, it's an obligation. The other thing is not
extending you the scope, it's telling you the order in which it's
done. Okay, but that's the pushback to say we're not extending the
scope.
So on the whole, that was a question, whether it has to
be a... I mean, because we have it over there, בר קמיה
דאופנא.
bar
kammai d'ofna.
We're not dealing with that question now. We're dealing with whether the
relatives can redeem. קרובים? Krovim? No, no, no. גאולת קרובים Geulas Krovim
is a different story, but if it's not a קרוב karov doing
it, you can't buy... I don't know if you could borrow money
from a קרוב, karov, but okay, but קרובים Krovim is a separate
category, okay? איתמר. Itmar. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
הכא נמי קרוב קרוב קודם. hacha nami krov krov kodem. היכא איתמר
דרב נחמן בר יצחק? heicha itmar d'Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak? Where was
that originally said? This idea of that the Torah is ordering the
order of redemption? אהא דאיבעיא להו. aha deibay'u lehu. We asked the
other side of the question. Until now we've just been asking about
the house in בתי ערי חומה, batei arei choma. but you could
ask the other question: what's the story about an עבד עברי הנמכר
לישראל? Eved Ivri hanimkar leYisrael? Is he ניגאל בקרובים? nigoal bekrovim? Okay,
עבד עברי הנמכר לישראל, Eved Ivri hanimkar leYisrael, ניגאל בקרובים או אינו
ניגאל בקרובים? nigoal bekrovim o ein nigoal bekrovim? Okay, now so that's
a really interesting question. I mean that to me that feels like
a more pressing question, right, about slavery than about the question of
the שדה. sadeh. So does that, do the קרובים krovim have a
right to buy him back? Because remember the גמרא Gemara said yesterday
that there's a particular mandate by sold to a non-Jew because of
the concern of assimilation, right? But by sold to a Jew it's
a concern of עבדות, avdus, and it's not a real עבדות, avdus,
but it's not the concern of assimilation. Do you also have the
right of קרובים krovim to buy back? Okay, so אליבא דרבי לא
תיבעי לך. aliba deRabbi lo tibaye lach. According to Rabbi it's not
even a question. דאמר, De'amar, he said, you might remember this about
a week ago, מי שאינו ניגאל באלה ניגאל בשש, mi she'eino nigoal
be'eleh nigoal beshesh, that only somebody who's not redeemed by קרובים krovim
is redeemed in six years. Rabbi said that the guy who's redeemed
by קרובים, krovim, the עבד עברי Eved Ivri who's sold to a
non-Jew, does not go out in six years, and the converse is
true: the עבד עברי Eved Ivri who goes out in six years,
meaning sold to a Jew, does not go out by גאולת קרובים.
Geulas Krovim. Okay, so Rabbi's explicit that the עבד עברי Eved Ivri
who's sold to a Jew does not go out by גאולת קרובים.
Geulas Krovim. אמר לא מיפריק, Amar lo miphrik, he's not redeemed. כי
תיבעי לך אליבא דרבנן. Ki tibaye lach aliba deRabbanan. According to the
Rabbis who have not voiced an opinion on this, מאי? mai? ילפינן
שכיר שכיר? yalfinan sachir sachir? We make a גזירה שוה gezerah shavah
of שכיר שכיר sachir sachir of an עבד עברי Eved Ivri sold
to a Jew to one of a non-Jew and we don't דרשינן
darshen יגאלנו, yigalenu, we don't say יגאלנו yigalenu means only you shall
redeem him, but we make the גזירה שוה gezerah shavah and say
relatives can redeem? או דילמא יגאלנו, O dilma yigalenu, לזה ולא לאחר.
lezeh velo le'acher. I'm sorry, it's not only you, it's only this.
יגאלנו, Yigalenu, only the עבד עברי Eved Ivri sold to the non-Jew
can be redeemed by relatives and not another עבד עברי, Eved Ivri,
an עבד עברי Eved Ivri sold to Jews cannot be redeemed by
relatives. So what do we say? Okay, is an עבד עברי Eved
Ivri sold to Jews redeemed by relatives or not? תא שמע, Ta
shema, בכל גאולה תתנו. bechol geulah titnu. We're going to go through
the same proofs and that seem to extend the scope and we're
going to reject them. Give redemption in everything. לרבות בתים ועבד עברי.
Lerabbos batin ve'Eved Ivri. מאי לאו mai lav, בתי, בתי ערי חומה
ועבד עברי הנמכר לישראל? Batei Arei Chomah ve'Eved Ivri hanimkar leYisrael? Doesn't
isn't this extending the scope that קרובים krovim redeem a house in
a walled city and עבד עברי Eved Ivri sold to ישראל? Yisrael?
לא, עבד עברי הנמכר לעובד כוכבים. Lo, Eved Ivri hanimkar le'oved kochavim.
No, no, no, we're talking about things we already know it applies
to: an עבד עברי Eved Ivri sold to non-Jews,
a בית bayis in בתי ערי חומה... Batei Arei Chomah, I mean,
excuse me, a בית bayis in בתי חצרים Batei Chatzerim in the
unwalled cities, the things we already know are redeemed by קרובים. krovim.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so עבד עברי הנמכר לעובד כוכבים בהדיא
כתיב ביה, Eved Ivri hanimkar le'oved kochavim behedya kesiv bei, או דודו
או בן דודו יגאלנו? o dodo o ben dodo yigalenu? So what
do you need this בכל? bechol? No, ההוא לקובעו חובה ואפילו רבי
יהושע. hahu lekova chovah va'afilu Rabbi Yehoshua. Just like we said yesterday,
right, except here it's a little different. Before we said it's coming
to teach me the position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. It's coming
to teach me that it is a חובה chovah and not a
רשות. reshus. So בכל bechol doesn't extend the scope, it deepens the
obligation and to tell me חובה chovah not a רשות. reshus. Here
it's very interesting. The גמרא Gemara does a little shift. It says
even רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that says by everything else it's a
רשות, reshus, by שדה אחוזה Sdeh Achuzah it's a רשות, reshus, he
would agree by an עבד עברי Eved Ivri sold to a non-Jew
it's a חובה. chovah. The extra פסוק pasuk is to tell you
that everybody would say in the case of עבד, eved, קרובים krovim
is a חובה chovah and as רש"י Rashi says, look at רש"י,
Rashi, אפילו רבי יהושע דאמר גבי שדה אחוזה רשות הכא מודה דחובה,
afilu Rabbi Yehoshua de'amar gabei Sdeh Achuzah reshus hacha modeh dechovah, דלא
יטמע בעובדי כוכבים. delo yitma be'ovdei kochavim. Okay, so that's a nice
little twist. By an עבד עברי Eved Ivri who's נמכר nimkar to
non-Jews everybody says it's a חובה. chovah. Let's just finish this up.
Okay, תא שמע, מה תלמוד לומר יגאלנו יגאלנו יגאלנו ג' פעמים? ta
shema, matalmud lomar yigalenu yigalenu yigalenu gimmel pe'amim? לרבות כל הגאולות שניגאל
כסדר זה. lerabbos kol hageulos shenigoal kaseder zeh. So we think like
that's extending the scope of גאולת קרובים. Geulas Krovim. מאי לאו בתי
ערי חומה ועבד עברי הנמכר לישראל? mai lav Batei Arei Chomah ve'Eved
Ivri hanimkar leYisrael? Doesn't that extend the scope that קרובים krovim redeem
a house in a walled city and עבד עברי Eved Ivri sold
to ישראל? Yisrael? לא, lo, בתי חצרים ושדה אחוזה.
batei
chatzerim v'sadeh achuza.
No, no,
no, it's just things that we already know. It's בתי חצרים, Batei
Chatzerim, it's שדה אחוזה. Sdeh Achuzah. שדה אחוזה, sdeh achuzzah, עבד עברי
eved ivri sold to a non-Jew, so that's true. Why do you
need the פסוק pasuk יגאלנו? yig'allennu? בתי חצרים בהדיא כתיב בהו על
שדה הארץ יחשב. battei chatzeirim be'hedya kesiv behu al sdeh ha'aretz yeichashev.
Why do you need יגאלנו yig'allennu יגאלנו? yig'allennu? If it's not extending
the scope, what does it do? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק amar
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak ומקרוב קרוב קודם. u'mikkarov karov kodem. It's telling
you the order of the redemption of the קרובים. k'rovim. So again,
we have these two דרשות, drashos, ובכל גאולה תתנו u'v'chol geulah titnu
and יגאלנו yig'allennu יגאלנו yig'allennu יגאלנו. yig'allennu. Sounds like it's extending the
scope. Sounds like it's saying even an עבד עברי eved ivri who
is sold to a Jew, even a בית bayis of בתי ערי
חומה. Batei Arei Chomah... And the pushback is no, גאולת קרובים geulas
k'rovim is only by what's in the פסוקים: psukim: שדה
אחוזה sdeh achuzzah and a עבד עברי eved ivri sold to a
non-Jew. And these פסוקים psukim are doing other things. They're telling you
it's an obligation, not just a right, and they're telling you the
order of the redemption of the קרובים. k'rovim. Okay, we'll end with
this.
So a Hebrew slave sold to a Jew cannot be redeemed by
a relative?
I'm sorry, one more time.
Is the conclusion that a Hebrew...